[Music]
for a while I've kind of felt and
especially with the eruption of me too
and times up and all of these gender
dynamics becoming really central to the
culture it kind of feels like we're
we're stuck in a dysfunctional
relationship between men and women that
is now manifesting everywhere and Warren
you've you've done work with with
relationships for an awfully long time
do you see that parallel and if so what
do we do about it yes we are we are
definitely caught up in an in a
dysfunctional relationship that would be
kind men we know we're asking men to you
know to sort of express their feelings
recognizing that we're repressed we're
so repressed that we're the sex that
commit suicide and at a level of six
times to 6 to 1 over women and when
we're in our 20s and when we're 85 and
older at 1,350 percent greater amount
than women and if that's not
dysfunctional then tell me what is no
suicide is probably the ultimate so in
order for us so we are wanting men to
open up on the one hand and then we're
saying don't mansplain you've dominated
the conversation shut up this is time
for women to speak up this is time for
men to shut up so totally contradictory
messages that men are getting told that
they're filled with power and privilege
and yet walking around in reality
feeling shamed and fearful and that
women have a type of power that they're
not even allowed to talk about because
they're the ones with the power and the
monopoly over it so it's it's that is
about as dysfunctional as it can get
we have to understand that we have these
attractions to each other for for
fundamentally dysfunctional reasons we
were never designed to be functional we
were designed to survive and now we have
the opportunity for the first time in
human history to be functional as well
as surviving and this is a whole new
dialogue that needs to be together but
though feminists have monopolized that
dialogue of women good men bad women the
oppressed men as the oppressors and
that's about as dysfunctional as you can
structure a dialogue it's as it's like a
person going into their
being saying I came here because you
know my wife has filled with problems
and and I have been telling her what to
do for many years and she doesn't pay
any attention to my direction and she's
a 100% wrong on these 14 different items
and I'd like you to help align with me
to help you understand how wrong she is
by the way if you do align with me I
will continue hiring you as a therapist
I control the money but if you don't
align with me that'll be the end of you
as a therapist and we're basically
having feminists say to the world if you
want to teach in gender studies you have
this party ideology to follow you have
to believe you have to articulate that
men we live in a patriarchal world
dominated by men that made rules to
benefit men at the expense of women and
if you don't follow that ideology
there's not a chance in that you'll get
a job at any decent university unless
that ideology is at your forefront and
you just have your own unique ways which
we give you many unique ways no problem
at all as long as you have unique ways
of expressing that ideology as
effectively as possible to your to your
students and do not deviate from that or
allow anyone else to come into this
university to talk in a different way
about that and so you cannot define it
would be hard to write a novel with a
fictional situation that would be more
of a dysfunctional dialogue the the
monologue then the monologue that is
happening now well you know we've we
used to have a battle of the sexes
that's been historical but now we no
longer have a battle of the sexes we
have a war in which only one side has
shown up the other side called men have
put their heads in the sand and hope the
bullets will miss that's a dysfunctional
dialogue so what needs to happen to to
get out of this we need to start
communication training in first second
third grade so that everybody knows how
to listen to everyone so that the bully
so we see in the bully his vulnerability
or her vulnerability we see in the mean
girl her vulnerability or his vote her
vulnerability and we
we have people share what they're about
what their feelings are what their hurts
are what their pains are and all come
together to to do that this is already
this is just a theory in Denmark they're
doing this in younger grades and it's
been very helpful in helping them have a
much more constructive first second
third grade but I believe we also need
to do this not just in kindergarten
first second third grade but we went but
when our boys and girls are going
through that process we need to have
their parents go through it at the same
time because if kids come home learning
how to communicate to parents who do not
know how to communicate they will have a
lack of respect for their parents which
will undermine their ability to follow
their parents guidance and that will
destabilize the family and so this has
to all this is the number one agenda
that needs to occur so that's step one
step two is that men have to speak up
men have to be willing to risk their
careers as I certainly experienced
myself doing when I started speaking up
about these issues it was very clear to
me that I lost my standing ovations that
I used to have and the more I paid
attention to the dialogues that were
happening though the the discussions
that were happening in the men's groups
I formed by forms of 300 men's groups
and you know that John Lennon was what
you know joined one of them and and
those were those were ways where men
opened up and said what they felt in the
safety of other men who were saying gee
I didn't realize anybody else but me
felt that and so but then when many of
them and when I started to incorporate
those what I heard in the men's groups
when I started to incorporate men's pain
and feelings into my presentations of
two groups at colleges and universities
I found myself going from very large
standing ovations large audiences
standing ovations and always being
invited back to two or three more
speaking engagements versus slowly all
of that dwindled and I knew that if I
continued speaking and incorporating
men's feelings and fears
that I would continue to have fewer and
fewer speaking engagements and I had to
make a decision you know did I want to
have you know now that I saw the formula
that I want to be formula speak and have
a huge income and do very well and be
very respected and and and applauded or
did I want to go ahead and and try to
discover my best truth and speak up
about that and try to represent and
incorporate men and while still
retaining a compassion for women and and
and make that part of my life and my my
contribution and I decided at least I
would try to incorporate the best truth
that I could and that led to books like
the myth of male power and you know that
was that created a totally different
paradigm for what the male/female
relationship was about and questioned
the whole concept of men having power
redefined power is feeling obligated to
earn money that somebody else said that
the old definition of power feeling
obligated to earn money that somebody
else spent while he died sooner was not
a good definition of power that power
was really about controlling one's own
life and historically speaking survival
controlled our lives not human beings
our parents and grandparents didn't talk
about having Wrightson and they talked
about not rights but they talked about
responsibilities and obligations and
when I decided to become an author my
father just laughed and said you just
cannot make a dependable living as an
author that's not responsible and it
wasn't until I got my third book
advanced that he changed his mind and
said okay you've proven yourself to be
an exception to the rule but you know
that's a rule don't encourage any of
your kids to become an artist or an
author because they just won't be able
to resupport a family on that Robert Bly
talked about a father thirst in our
culture that we're all thirsty for this
energy and in a way you can look at the
success of Jordan Peterson as this great
need for that archetypal father figure
kind of offering discipline offering
rules for life offering meaning offering
purpose and your work the boy crisis
very much looks at what boys in
particular lacking does I guess that
what what do you think boys are lacking
from this absence of the father well
boys are lacking purpose we have a
purpose void and then we have a purpose
void combined with a dad void that has
left boys in an extremely precarious
place by a purpose void it used to be
that we had to sense of two ways of
having purpose in the past to be a
potential warrior we would be called
hero if we were risking our lives to die
and or we would wear the sole
breadwinner in a matter what type of
personality we had if we were to be a
man we not only had to raise enough
money to support ourselves but to
support our wives and in the 19 and in
the 19th century it was often 10
children my father was one of 10
children and he was expected to his
father was expected to support you know
11 people actually 12 people himself his
wife and in all 10 children and so
that's a huge amount of economic
pressure to take jobs that are not
fulfilling but jobs that are oftentimes
deadening so that you can earn that type
of money and so and so now when we have
this purpose void and we have a dad void
there is debt that the boys without
fathers do have a father thirst and and
they don't know where to go especially
in a world where the culture isn't
saying to them well you have two places
to go you can be a you can you'll be
disposable as a warrior or you can be
you know do something you may not want
to do to in order to support be the sole
breadwinner for your family not to worry
okay I don't have a father he died in
war or whatever but at least I have the
culture telling me I have to clear
senses of purpose not true anymore
and it's good that we have a purpose
void for boys it's just terrible that we
have a purpose void for boys at a time
that we don't have that the ability of
we oftentimes and many families don't
have a father to direct male
testosterone
toward a constructive purpose because
when male testosterone is not directed
toward a constructive purpose it ends up
being directed toward a disruptive
purpose and it's a very powerful force
so I now know as a result of the
research for the boy crisis that
boys who that if we look at all Isis
recruits almost all the Isis recruits
have in common one thing they are either
boys or girls who don't have a
significant amount of father involvement
when we look at the school shooters or
the mass shooters they are almost all
boys who don't have a significant amount
of father involvement when we look at
prisoners we know that the only women's
centers that we have in the United
States we though we have many we know
that we have many women's centers in the
United States but we also feel like you
know where are the men's centers and we
do have men's centers they're called
prisons and the prisons are filled with
about 93 percent males but what we don't
know is that very almost the common
denominator of those males is lack of
father involvement I just checked this
out with the chief judge of the Superior
Court of Washington DC and he told me
and the other family court judges told
me that in fact is well over 90 percent
of the people in prison who are males
are males without significant father
involvement and so I discovered in just
a hundred different ways that when
children don't have their fathers they
have significant amounts of problems but
boys in particular have a greater amount
of problems because they don't have a
role model they don't have a way to find
themselves as a male we often do rite of
passage programs but rite of passage is
only a minimal substitute for the real
rite of passage which is a father
everyday interacting with his child to
learn when to take risks when not to
take risks when to be assertive when
does a certain us become aggressiveness
the this happens from everyday
roughhousing with dads where does say no
that went too far you can't do that if
you if you could continue to push your
sister around your brother around
there'll be no more roughhousing
it comes from dads enforcing the
boundaries they set that no more
roughhousing means no more roughhouse
it comes from dad's not taking that
boundary and that punishment too far it
means it means no more roughhousing
until tomorrow night
but you so you'll have no more pleasure
tonight and more excitement tonight if
you because you bullied or you pushed
your sister your brother but we'll help
we'll continue it tomorrow night but in
the meantime here's the thing five
things you need to do you need to get
your teeth brushed you need to get
finish your homework you need to do
something else and then we'll have more
reading time or some other type of time
together and so we need to understand
that children both boys and girls need
to bond with their dads dads and dads
are very good at creating a bond through
the excitement of things like
roughhousing they are very good about
helping children be trusted to go out of
their comfort zone if a boy or girl
comes home from school and says you know
mrs. Moyers hates me you know let's
let's I don't want to be involved in her
with her class anymore and moms will
tend to say sweetie
I don't want you to have a bad
experience in education at a very young
age because it could be fundamental so
I'll go in and talk to mrs. Jones the
principal about transferring you from
mrs. Moyes class to mrs. whoever calls
class and so the and so but whereas Dad
is more likely to say sweetie you know
you've got to learn to get along with
people that you don't that don't like
you and that you don't like so what can
we do to talk to you know what would
mrs. Moyers say about you and what is
heart what are her complaints about you
and and then you know the boy is
encouraged to talk about taking
accountability and responsibility and
moving through to another level and
getting out of his comfort zone as
opposed to having his because his
comfort zone catered to these are these
and about 10 other examples like this of
our different the differences in dads
style parenting that need to be combined
with the best of mom style parenting so
that the the protection and the
nurturance and the unconditional
manifestations of love that mothers tend
to give are very important to creating
the security blankets of children but
it's also important in creating the
security
blankets of children that children be
guided out of their comfort zone not
just during a rite of passage but during
every day of their life with consistency
that helps them know that that my dad is
pushing me yes but my dad is there for
me he's pushing me because he loves me
he has an unconditional love also it's
differently manifested than mom's
unconditional love and his unconditional
love is not giving unconditional
approval but giving approval and
disapproval but when we when we do
things that are related to a healthy
masculinity rather than a toxic
masculinity or a healthy femininity not
using my social skills as a girl to be
able to manipulate or my attractiveness
as a girl to be able to manipulate a boy
into doing something for me that he
wouldn't do out of his own interest
except for the fact that he believes
that I'll have a relationship with me or
sex with me and I see how vulnerable he
is in this area that's an example of
toxic femininity and if Ana father can
help a girl through that process as well
you talk with jordan peterson about
about this what do you make because for
me his success signifies how much we're
thirsting for this father energy in our
culture what do you make of jordan
peterson what do you make of the jordan
Peterson phenomena you know I think
first of all I would not have predicted
it so I don't want to I I think maybe
I'm often called and among my among my
people who agree with me I'm called a
visionary and but I was not a visionary
and for seeing Jordan Peterson I think
it's amazing that an intellectual that
is young in who is you know who speaks
in terms of often of metaphor and an
allegory that he has risen to such
extraordinary success and I think it is
in part a result of our enormous hunger
we you know we have we have attached to
two extremely unlikely figures because
it our hunger the Donald Trump on the
one hand and Jordan Peter said on the
other two ends of the extreme in terms
of somebody who's been willing is
say you know fathers are important
families are important and so Jordan and
I found ourselves in a hour-and-a-half
dialogue in which I would give a you
know I would talk about fathers and
roughhousing and he would talk about
some intellectual Piaget or someone else
who was you know who was in the
literature or in Disney movies or
something else that related to that and
it was just a fascinating
hour-and-a-half I I think because you
know I'm usually when I'm being
interviewed I don't learn a great deal
but I certainly learned it was wonderful
the way we learned from each other and
you know in our workshops what we work a
lot with is men owning their shadow
owning the fact that we have an
aggressive side we have there is a
predatory element to male sexuality all
of this sort of stuff and integrating it
understanding accepting and integrating
it and this this to me at least sort of
points away potentially through the
dynamics that were seeing at the moment
to be able to accept the shadow side of
masculinity and then stand in in in in
our own power as men there's much less
talk in that in our culture about the
shadow side of femininity the shadow
side of women and that seems really
unbalanced yes absolutely and that's
exactly in my opinion accurate we're
talking about the I just spoke at a
conference called a wellness conference
and Idaho and many many of the
presentations were on the the divine
female but there were no presentations
on the male of the female shadow or the
you know the the less than divine well
if you will and yet there is a huge
amount of cultural conversation on the
and the male shadow which we aren't even
gentle enough to call the shadow when
you hear the word male shadow that
implies men who are being introspective
about integrating the shadow side of
themselves into the rest of themselves
and and having an acceptance of that
and and are trying to become holistic as
men but when you hear the statements
about male privilege and male power that
comes from a political ideological place
that really doesn't allow and that you
and those men go into college and they
can't speak up without calling it being
told oh you're just mansplaining so
we're telling the boys and men on the
one hand
share your feelings and then the moment
men share their feelings they go your
mansplaining and that's sort of like
excuse me what did I hear and certainly
you know a guy that's in class in
college and that is being sharing his
his heart and his pain and his shame and
his and his shadow side openly and he
notices that women withdraw from him in
the class but if he had an interest in
taking somebody out and asking somebody
out in the classroom that that would be
that would undermine his ability to be
successful in making that contact so we
have a huge amount of problem and so
what I said before about we've taken a
magnifying glass we've taken our
binoculars and we've used our binoculars
to look at women's experience of
powerlessness and women's experience of
male power but we haven't looked at
men's experience of powerlessness and
men's experience of female power that's
a problem we're looking only at one side
of the equation and we've done that for
a half a century and it's so important
that the conversation become more
balanced male/female dynamics are an
evolutionary tango in which every time
you change any part of the dance you
have to look at both sides of that dance
changing women do not worship men who
are expressing their feelings and
they're they're going to you know
they're the first signs of what women
are interested in is the cheerleader is
cheering for the football player which
the the the the the foot the
cheerleaders are saying hit him again
hit him again harder harder or first and
ten do it again then first and ten do it
again is first and ten
a concussion again first thing at 10:00
risk a dislocated shoulder spinal cord
injury again because if you take that
piece of leather a hundred yards in a
car and it goes you go across into the
gully into the end zone we will like you
more we will love you more boys are
getting the message that girls like them
and love them when they risk their
bodies because that's historically and
evolutionary preparation for them
risking their bodies as firefighters as
in the military being disposable we have
we haven't had no conversation about the
pressure on boys and men to be
disposable what I call the social bribes
as social bribes from fathers from
mothers from from women from men to be
willing to be if you go to war and you
serve in the military or you're an elite
Navy SEAL that you will be called a hero
if you are the the male who is willing
to die as a volunteer firefighter you're
getting no pay economically all of your
pay is the social bribe of respect of
honor of women being more attracted to
you and your firefighting uniform and
that is your pay but you have to realize
that that pay is a social bribe for you
to be disposable so that women and other
men can be protected it's one thing for
you to understand that as your social
bribe to be disposable it's another
thing to allow yourself to have that
cold male power and privilege when in
fact it's male disposability I'd love to
hear you kind of summarize where you
came from I think you've got a really
interesting perspective having been part
of the women's movement and and then
you're you're now kind of seen as the
father of the men's movement yes yeah
it's ironic I start yes yeah and I did
start out when I was doing my doctorate
at New York University the women's I was
teaching at Rutgers University at the
time and when the women's movement
surfaced I started incorporating that
into my political science curriculum as
a political movement and my advisors and
I was also doing my
doctoral dissertation at the time and so
the students and at Rutgers were saying
man when you speak about the women's
movement you got fire in your belly and
yeah you should think you know what are
you doing your dissertation on and I
said what I was doing it on which was a
different part of politics and they said
you should think about doing it on
something about the women's movement so
I went to my to my Advisory Committee
and they said oh you know Warren you
don't want to sort of like demean
yourself with taking on some little fad
that's going to be going away in a few
years and I said I don't think this is a
fair that's going to be going away I
think this is a an evolutionary shift
where women are beginning to speak up
and say the old gender roles of the past
were too rigid we're more than just a
role and I think that this is going to
have implications for both women and men
however I do agree that it's a lot of
hostility toward men and you know and it
may take a little bit longer to catch on
among men and so they said if you really
want to go for it but that got me deeply
involved and then that led to my being
elected to the board of directors of the
National Organization for Women in New
York City and then I got reelected for a
few years after that and so I spoke all
around the world on women's issues the
importance of women's issues and why any
secure man should be a supporter of
women being having more flexible roles
and and also the importance of this for
men and for men to be a part of this
process and this was a place where Betty
Ford Ann and I agreed very strongly
Betty Ford and ended up writing us a
book called second-stage that didn't get
nearly as much publicity as the as the
feminine mystique but when she did that
she said that the second stage of the
women's movement needed to be men having
more flexible roles as well and this she
and I had discussed this and many times
and we both strongly agreed that this is
where it needed to go unfortunately the
women's movement started moving in a
direction that was much less male
friendly in the and the key turning
point in my relationship with now in New
York City was that the
many women who were divorced we're
writing into the board and saying I
don't like your whole equality policy
because that means that men and women
have equal rights to the children after
divorce when in fact I know what's best
for my children the mothers would say
and so if I want to marry a new man
start a new life move out of the state
and keep my children away from the
father I should be allowed to do that
and I said whoa you're talking about
females doing what is best for them
without asking what is best for the
children and so I started doing some
research on this and I said from what I
can tell it looks like the children do
best when they have about an equal
amount of mother and father involvement
after divorce and unless we find out
otherwise that should be where we stand
the fact that that was the the point
that you kind of found yourself in
conflict with links very much into the
book that you've now your new book which
is the effect that that has often on
boys what led me to doing the boy crisis
was as I was speaking around the country
when when why men are the way they are
it got translated into a lot of
languages and as did the myth of male
power and that led me to speaking in
countries like Japan and Germany and
Australia New Zealand etc and in many of
those countries after my talks teachers
would say you know I'm seeing something
happen in my classroom the boys are
really struggling a lot and they're
falling a lot behind girls and in my
particular school you know both of the
valedictorian of the salutatorian and
most of the Honor Society of the
equivalent thereof is almost 70 80 %
girls and so that alerted me to
something is happening here my sister
was a teacher she said the same thing
and so I know this was yes quite a while
ago this is back in the 70s I began to
hear about this maybe even in the 80s
70s and 80s divorces were happening in
large numbers and I was beginning to see
and my sister and other people would say
you know a lots of times when the
families break up the
the the the kids that are otherwise
doing well especially the boys seemed to
really fall-off in motivation and
attitude and send withdraw and but those
were all just pieces of information but
I began to feel like there was something
there to that so the first thing I
noticed was that the boy crisis was
happening when the United Nations
authorized a study called pasa of tests
that were being done of children and in
the largest developed nations and in the
less developed nations well when I
sorted out the 63 nations the largest
developed nations all the developed
nations had boys falling significantly
behind girls and almost all of their
academic subjects so I started asking
why and looked at the fact that
developed nations had permission for two
things to happen one was for there to be
a divorces and for women to be able to
usually in most countries the women had
more priority if they said that there
was any challenge with the man or most
judges wanted the children to be
involved with both parents but if a
woman objected to that most judges were
afraid to go against the woman's
objection because if the woman says she
was afraid of the man and any one thing
happened at any point in the future the
judges career could be in jeopardy and
so most judges heard in the in the
direction of protecting the mom from the
you know any possible undesirability of
the father so that was happening in the
divorce area and then a huge thing was
happening in throughout most of the
world in the developed world which was
that as the world as the developed
nations had less preoccupation with
survival they gave more permission to
women for women to have children without
being devout being married and in that
group I noticed that there was a huge
divide also as there was in the divorce
be people the the mother so in the
United States to be very clear 53
percent of women under 30 who have
children have children without being
married
now marriage to per se is not a big
thing from my perspective but it turns
out to be a huge thing in terms of the
possibility the probability that
children will have contact with their
dads in unmarried when women have
children without being married there's a
relatively small chance that those
children will have long term contact
with their fathers and so I was
beginning to see this enormous gap
between children that had had contact
with their fathers that was that were
consistent and that was significant and
children that did not and the children
that had a lot of contact with their
fathers even if they were in divorced
families or they were unmarried families
that small percentage of children that
did have good contact with their fathers
did quite well not as well as it an
intact family but close to it and then
conversely the children that had minimal
or no contact with their fathers were
doing terribly as a rule and more than
that I was altum Utley able to research
that to them for the boy crisis book to
the point where I was able to identify
seventy different ways that children do
so much worse with their fathers this is
true of girls and boys but it was more
true of boys the intensity level and the
degree of and the numbers of areas were
greater with the boys why a boy is
affected more than girls I think the
number one reason is that when a girl
has a single mom she has a role model
when a boy has no a single mom he does
not have a role model as to how to be a
male second the culture has given girls
much more many more options recently
they a girl who's married can and having
a child she has the option to be to work
full-time to be involved with the
children full-time or to do some
combination of both and we're you know
the the since the feminist movement has
occurred one of the good things that's
happened for women and girls is that we
say be whoever you want to be but we
don't say to boys you know when the
children arrive you you and your wife
should discuss who will be
the primary parent and you have as much
right to be and expect and expectation
to be the primary parent as the mom does
for the most for the most part the young
male who's married who's about to have
to be a father says you know I have
three options to I can you know work
full-time or I can work full-time or I
can work full-time and and there are
certainly an increased percentage of
dads who are full-time dads but it's
really still about nine eight ten
percent depending on the country and the
and that and and among those men is a
much greater likelihood of divorce if
the man doesn't do something at home
that produces money so long story short
the the the great majority of single
mothers do not have boys that see a
great deal of their father's and the boy
doesn't have the old senses of purpose
and the in the old days there used to be
if up you were a boy the culture told
you you have two options you can be a
warrior and be a hero and be respected
by us and you could be a sole
breadwinner and so you knew that you had
to march to one of those two tunes or
both of those choose tunes be a warrior
or sole breadwinner now we need many
fewer warriors and we need women are
sharing the bread with this the bread
winning role so a man doesn't have to
define himself as a man by being a sole
breadwinner and yet at the same time if
he's not a sole breadwinner there's a
challenge there as well so a boy has to
sort out what do I want to be if there's
there's a purpose void in the culture
for boys there's not a purpose void in
the culture for girls there's multiple
purposes for girls and so a boy without
a father and with a purpose void has a
purpose void combined with a dad void
and the dad void and the purpose void
put together our disasters for a boy
because a dad whose constructive and
involved is a dad who can channel the
testosterone toward two things helping
his son say what's your unique
characteristics my sweet
man and then secondly no matter what
your unique characteristics are and no
matter what fulfills you you have to
also be responsible for earning income
so you have to balance this sense of
fulfillment which I want to support just
but just make sure that you know that
the more fulfilling a job is the less
it's likely to pay and so therefore when
you do a fulfilling job don't neglect
don't just say oh I can do anything I
want to do because most women won't be
interested in you and you will not feel
you're producing for the family and and
contributing in a in an honest way and
so you've got to combine this but
combining being fulfilled with producing
responsible income that can help produce
support both yourself and share the
support of your children that's a tough
combination and without a father figure
there to help a a move through that pit
is very challenging whereas girls have
the support of both the culture they
don't have a purpose void they have an
expansion of purpose and they have a
female role model which the for her
being growing up as a as a productive
woman the boy does not have a male role
model and so that's one of the those are
two of the major reasons that boys fall
so far behind girls I also teach men's
work and what's interesting is there's a
lot in the culture at the moment around
kind of me too and times up and male
behavior really acting men really acting
out but there's another side to it as
well I mean what I often see from the
men coming to the workshops that we're
doing is a sense of shame around
themselves as men of castration of
internalized yeah internalized shame
around themselves exactly hashtag me to
is wonderful up to a point it's
wonderful in the sense that we want
women to speak up and say where they're
where they've been offended where
they've been hurt where they've been
misused the
a necessary speech set of feelings
excellent and there's more to men and
women than women only
there is men and women are men as well
as women they're boys as well as girls I
talk in the boy crisis I quote a real
life you know slam poem from a fellow
named Royce man and he goes you know I
am walking on the street and I see in
front of me a woman who looks back at me
and she sees that I am behind her so she
crosses the street to the other side and
then I discover how I should be a man
how I should what is it is to be a man
is I am a person who is yes I'll be a
father
yes I'll be a brother but I'll also be
an attacker what am i as a man I am
mostly and at an attacker I am mostly an
attacker what shame is built into that
and that went viral and that went viral
because so many males identify with that
shame and so many women say yes that's
what you should feel you should feel
that sense of humbleness to the point of
shame at representing and being a white
male and when you go to college if you
express these feelings of powerlessness
understand this is a time for women to
speak up this is a time for men to shut
up so you have white male privilege so
shut up
that's not a good way to bring a man
into society as a healthy man now look I
look at Trump for example and I sense
that we're so starving for genuine male
qualities that people have elected what
is effectively a facsimile of these
strong male qualities as president does
that scan for you yeah yes or no I was I
was an adviser to four advisors from the
Clinton
pain and it was a strong supporter of
her effort to become president and and I
kept saying to the advisors that that
there's two major things happening in
this country one is that boys are having
significant problems and that no one is
articulating that and and that if you
Hillary speak up about boys problems no
feminist is going to leave you because
you're speaking about boys problems
because they're alternative is Donald
Trump that's the last thing a feminist
wants to vote for so you can speak up
about these problems and with political
safety and with political enhancement
because you can because people who are
moderate Republicans and our parents and
are having a dysfunctional son who's a
failure to launch will say my goodness
somebody cares about my son and most
people care more about their children
than they care about a political label
and so the know this is completely safe
for you to do she could not do that
secondly she I said there's it's
working-class families that are having
that are there are not okay with so much
focus being on LGBTQ and so little focus
being on the struggles that they're
dealing with when they you know when
they've been trained as a coal miner and
they've lost their their coal jobs they
need to be empathize with and then they
need to know that there's going to be a
transition that you will help install to
move them from their olds levels of
security to new levels of security and
it is not just the men who care about
this because most of these men are
heterosexuals they're married to women
who are dependent on them for their
income and said if you don't pay
attention to them their wives also feel
threatened and sure enough 52% of non
African American women have vote voted
for Trump and so I feel like that the
emphasis of the Democratic Party
in terms of closing out discussions on
on family values on the value of fathers
the demon is the combination of the
demonization of men
and the undervaluing of the family led
men and women who loved men and boys who
were having problems with not being seen
heard and not having any place to go and
what they what they found was some man
who was probably the most who was
probably the best personification of the
immature shadow of masculinity that we
could possibly dig up and have go
anywhere and in and that spoke with that
type of anger and honesty and and
honesty is one of his good traits his
own perception of honesty and spoke up
without fear which is one of his good
traits being able to speak up about
things other people that are unwilling
to say and they heard in him not just a
political way of being but an emotional
way of being that mimicked their way of
shouting out and making things crystal
clear black and white and being so sure
and so solid about that that they ended
up supporting his attitude even though
his attitude much much about him
contradicted what their Christian values
are contradicted with their values of
being modest and and not being a bracket
there are parts I've read some media
coverage which kind of paints you as the
patron saint of the men's rights
activists and angry and regressive
troglodyte all of those kind of all of
those words are kind of lodged in your
direction what what do you make of that
why do you think that happens and how do
you how do you respond yes I almost
never had somebody read the myth of male
power and say this is an angry book and
I've never had it's rare that somebody I
don't think I've had a single person
read the boy crisis book and say this is
an angry book where this doesn't work to
put help men and women understand each
other
I and
I have maybe spoken a thousand times in
a thousand places I have had that one
demonstration that but only one in a
thousand you know speaking engagements
and the and and I don't I don't know
no one said during that demonstration I
read the myth of male power carefully
you know I even read it and this is the
problems I have with it let's sit down
and have a dialogue about it and at the
same time so since I believe in taking
responsibility I have allowed myself to
defend and be associated with people in
the men's rights movement such as Paul
Elam and and even though I disagree with
much of the content of what they say the
very fact that I'm willing to say listen
hear them behind every angry face is
somebody who once heard and then it's
listened to has their anger dilute
diluted so if you want to not just be
angry at the angry people or hate the
hate the haters you know instead of
being like them be open to what they're
saying they all we all have a truth to
speak and so that has allowed me to be
associated with as as opposed to just
rejecting the messages but I think that
personality wise I tend to be at the up
you know I tend to be not like the
Valerie Solanas of society for cutting
up men
author feminists and at the same time
not like the the the men's rights
movement people who are make tau people
who are saying I have to go my own way
it's a hopeless Society I'm here
speaking today and around the world all
the time because I still do have hope
although I think we are as you said in a
very dysfunctional relationship so I
feel like a therapist in a very
dysfunctional relationship where one of
the people in the relationship is
accusing me of being on there and the
others on the wrong side their spouses
side
you